<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Religions on Farooq's</title><link>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/</link><description>Recent content in Religions on far.chickenkiller.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>(C) Some rights are reserved under CC-BY-SA 4.0 for Farooq Karimi Zadeh</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 17:41:51 +0330</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What kind of a God we have?</title><link>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/what-kind-of-a-god-we-have/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 08:29:49 +0330</pubDate><guid>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/what-kind-of-a-god-we-have/</guid><description>
&lt;p>In our small circle of Quran researchers, someone, named Aqil Suleimani was questioning our imaginations about God. That is, do we know God in Islam well? And does our definition of God, and what he does, match with Quran?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Do we know God? Or maybe we have wrong assumptions? People say why does God let bad people do whatever they want and murder innocent people? Did Quran say God would prevent such people from killing, murdering and jailing?&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Then he asks a question. How does God decide who to save and who to let perish among believers and the Prophets?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Why does God save Abraham from Fire? But he lets people saw Zechariah and kill him? Why did God help Muslims in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Badr" target="_blank">Badr&lt;/a> but did not help them in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Uhud" target="_blank">Uhud&lt;/a>? Why didn&amp;rsquo;t God save people in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People_of_the_Ditch" target="_blank">Ukhdud&lt;/a>?&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I think he is asking a good question. More examples from me, God lets people behead John. But then he rescues Jesus(according to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_in_Islam" target="_blank">the Islamic account&lt;/a>). He also saves Moses, Noah and their followers. But then he lets corrupt Jews kill several Prophets. We have some sayings from the Prophet Muhammad that God inspires 60 Prophets in a day and they kill them all. Or that God sends a Prophet in the morning, another one in the noon and finally another one in the evening and they kill them all. God does not save them. But according to the Old Testament account, he saves Elias and Daniel. And many many other examples.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This leads us to a question:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Among believers and the Prophets, who does God save and who he lets people kill them? And why? How does God decide who to save?&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>A God who does not care</title><link>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/a-god-who-does-not-care/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 10:52:21 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/a-god-who-does-not-care/</guid><description>
&lt;p>There are many doctrines which suggest there is a god but one who does not
care about his servants and that they worship him or not. Here, I want to argue why we cannot make such an assumption. As the assumption is equal to the assumption which in it there is no god at all.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Here, we are interested in the outcomes which come from God.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is an outcome if God cares.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If there is a God and he does not care, the outcome is zero.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If there is no God, outcome is again zero.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If there is a God who cares, there is some outcome. That is, this God punishes or rewards based on deeds.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Assumption about that God doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist is equal to that God exists but does not care.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Obviously, a god who cares does something and therefore, because of his deed about his servants, there is an outcome, positive or negative.&lt;/p>
&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://far.chickenkiller.com/cactus.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="http://far.chickenkiller.com/style.css" type="text/css">
&lt;div id="comment-section">&lt;/div>
&lt;script>
window.onload = () => initComments({
node: document.getElementById("comment-section"),
defaultHomeserverUrl: "https://matrix.cactus.chat:8448",
serverName: "cactus.chat",
siteName: "far.chickenkiller.com",
commentSectionId: "a-god-who-does-not-care.md"
})
&lt;/script></description></item><item><title>Origin of Iron on Earth</title><link>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/origin-of-iron-on-earth/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 15:29:43 +0430</pubDate><guid>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/origin-of-iron-on-earth/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Some of the readers might wonder what is this post doing in the &amp;ldquo;Religion&amp;rdquo; categories of my website.
If you are one of those, you will get the answer of your question after reading this entire small post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to &lt;a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn27570-supernova-space-bullets-could-have-seeded-earths-iron-core/" target="_blank">some researches&lt;/a> the origin of Iron found on Earth is from the space out of Earth,
Mostly from stars which are near to their death.
The researches which a wide range of scientists have agreement upon, suggest that near the end of a star&amp;rsquo;s life, the star converts all its atoms to Oxygen and Carbon, and later Iron.
After that the star explodes, spreading all its atoms including iron ones into space, which later could form planets like our Earth.
Surprisingly, Quran tells us that God has &amp;ldquo;sent down&amp;rdquo; Iron in &lt;a href="https://quran.com/57/25" target="_blank">verse 57:25&lt;/a> which is in Hadid Surah/chapter which translated to English means Iron. Here&amp;rsquo;s the translation of the verse by Dr. Khattab:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Indeed, We sent Our messengers with clear proofs, and with them We sent down the Scripture and the balance ˹of justice˺ so that people may administer justice. And We sent down iron with its great might, benefits for humanity, and means for Allah to prove who ˹is willing to˺ stand up for Him and His messengers without seeing Him. Surely Allah is All-Powerful, Almighty.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>One meaning of &amp;lsquo;Anzalna&amp;rsquo; in Arabic means &lt;code>giving&lt;/code> or &lt;code>favoring&lt;/code> but the other meaning is &lt;code>sending down something from the sky to earth or (probably) from up to down&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Indeed, one can find verses in Quran which suprises them, if they go deep enough.&lt;/p>
&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://far.chickenkiller.com/cactus.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="http://far.chickenkiller.com/style.css" type="text/css">
&lt;div id="comment-section">&lt;/div>
&lt;script>
window.onload = () => initComments({
node: document.getElementById("comment-section"),
defaultHomeserverUrl: "https://matrix.cactus.chat:8448",
serverName: "cactus.chat",
siteName: "far.chickenkiller.com",
commentSectionId: "origin-of-iron-on-earth.md"
})
&lt;/script></description></item><item><title>How to Study Quran?</title><link>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/how-to-study-quran/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 15:30:50 +0330</pubDate><guid>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/how-to-study-quran/</guid><description>
&lt;p>&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="https://farooqkz.de1.hashbang.sh/count/tag.svg" alt="dot for stats" />
&lt;/figure>&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="thanks-to-narges-aalizadeh-from-iran-for-reading-and-editing-this-post">Thanks to Narges Aalizadeh from Iran for reading and editing this post&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Quran is a text and book which Muslims, followers of the one who claimed to be a prophet named Muhammad, believe about 1400 years ago it was sent down
to their prophet from Allah or God(the former is the special name for God in Arabic).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I share my thoughts as an amateur Quran researcher for others in the hope that these notes would be useful for others. I have not got any certificate or anything from religious schools or whatever. I am a simple programmer(Python and Javascript mostly) who sometimes does some research on this text.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Quran is like a deep ocean. If there is something in nature which can be compared to Quran, it would be a deep and big ocean.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you had pleasure to read a mathematics or computer science text, you would know that you may not understand a text by reading it once or twice. Sometimes even reading &lt;em>a lot&lt;/em> will not help. But when you you learn a mathematical concept in a chapter and read about it again in the other chapter, that&amp;rsquo;s what helps you understand it much better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Quran is not about CS or Mathematics but still a very deep text. To understand a sentence in Quran these tips can help:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Know the words. Every single word matters.&lt;/strong> A word may have multiple meanings in Arabic. Just like in English but sometimes worse, perhaps a lot worse. Also sometimes a word in Arabic can be so precise. Like there is a word in Arabic which means a number from 6 to 9(see the beginning of the Surah (or Chapter) Rome).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Read and research on similar ayat.&lt;/strong> There are topics which Quran talks about them in various places. For example it talks about story of Moses and the King of Egypt, Pharaoh, in multiple Surat such as Taha(20th Surah) and Jonah or Yunes which is the 10th Surah. Sometimes an ayah or a series of ayat explain what a single ayah does not. As an example you may not know what does 73:15 talk about just by reading this single ayah. E.g. Who was that messenger?&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Read and research on Hadiths.&lt;/strong> There are topics which the Hadiths, Muhammad&amp;rsquo;s sayings and doings, explain about. It&amp;rsquo;s always good to do a text search on different Hadith books such as Sahih Bukhari or Sahih Muslim or other books.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Please email me any comment you have:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>fkz at riseup dot net
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://far.chickenkiller.com/cactus.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="http://far.chickenkiller.com/style.css" type="text/css">
&lt;div id="comment-section">&lt;/div>
&lt;script>
window.onload = () => initComments({
node: document.getElementById("comment-section"),
defaultHomeserverUrl: "https://matrix.cactus.chat:8448",
serverName: "cactus.chat",
siteName: "far.chickenkiller.com",
commentSectionId: "how-to-study-quran.md"
})
&lt;/script></description></item><item><title>2 years with a Jinn living inside me</title><link>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/2-years-with-a-jinn-living-inside-me/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 12:28:08 +0330</pubDate><guid>http://far.chickenkiller.com/religion/2-years-with-a-jinn-living-inside-me/</guid><description>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Updated on 2023-07-16&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Oh Jinn? What is that? I think the best English translation for this Arabic word is “Demon”. But I am gonna use the Arabic word to make sure I refer to the one described in Islam. You might find it surprising that someone believes in something like this, which seems to be some legend from former ignorant people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a fact, proving or disproving existence of such a thing is impossible. But as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertrand_Russell" target="_blank">Russell&lt;/a> argued in the 20th century, this does not allow us to believe in anything which its existence is impossible to disprove.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, this belief of me in Islam, make me get myself out of trouble. During the summer before 12nd grade, I was studying hard for Conquer, a big exam in Iran in which people go university through it, and everything was fine before something terrible happen to me: Suddenly and at once he was not able to study and code and sometimes not even plain reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also some other weird stuff happened to me at the same time. I had lost many functionallities of my body. The worst part was that I could not use my hand and fingers for typing, which is necessary for programming and writing which is necessary for mathematics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I messed school exams up and the more important exam which was Conquer as well. After about two years, I learned about healing through Quran and praying. I also learned about “Sihr”(Black magic) and “Hasad”(Envy). There are different kinds of Sihr and one of them is a Sihr which could ruin success of a successful person(for example a successful student) and turn them into someone with a lot of faults and no success. Hasad could have such an effect, too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I got a recipe from someone and listened to Quran reciting voice everyday. In the beginning listening to Quran was hard for me like a burden. Additionally, listening to Quran was making me angry wanting to break stuff or throw stuff away. I could listen to Quran without having any problem before this period. I was told, when I listen Quran, the Jinn who has possessed me gets pressured and so he/she pressures me to make me stop listening and I had to do the opposite.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I listened to Quran till I got my ability for mind tasks like coding and math back. After this, I am highly confident if I ever disbelieve in Islam and in God.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to God, then three people who gave me consults.&lt;/p>
&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://far.chickenkiller.com/cactus.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="http://far.chickenkiller.com/style.css" type="text/css">
&lt;div id="comment-section">&lt;/div>
&lt;script>
window.onload = () => initComments({
node: document.getElementById("comment-section"),
defaultHomeserverUrl: "https://matrix.cactus.chat:8448",
serverName: "cactus.chat",
siteName: "far.chickenkiller.com",
commentSectionId: "2-years-with-a-jinn-living-inside-me.md"
})
&lt;/script></description></item></channel></rss>